<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-28T03:41:51+00:00</updated><id>https://meakbiyik.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>AI researcher, entrepreneur, wine enthusiast, occasional blogger. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">On the unsightly science of architecture</title><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/evasive-architecture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the unsightly science of architecture"/><published>2025-01-01T00:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-01T00:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/evasive-architecture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/evasive-architecture/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/photo_2025-01-01_17-25-42-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/photo_2025-01-01_17-25-42-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/photo_2025-01-01_17-25-42-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/photo_2025-01-01_17-25-42.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Kornhaus over the Limmat river, Zürich. The grey middle finger.</figcaption> </figure> <p>I asked many architecture students in Zürich what they thought of Kornhaus, a local symbol of brutalism. Most seemed bored by the question, possibly due to the regularity of the event, and the contempt in their response correlated with their appreciation of the building. “Concrete,” one said, “the choice of concrete and other materials”, when I asked what made that grey rectangle remarkable.</p> <p>As with these students building our bleak, rectangular future, I have talked with other weary experts. One regionally renowned wine critic, when I inquired, used “flawless” as his highest praise about some soulless, oaky red wine. A gourmet described their branch of celery as “crunchy and delicious” in the second course of their fancy fine dining experience. I asked myself then: what unites these exhausted groups of people, showing the tendency to gratify a simple and ugly option over any other?</p> <p>Three reasons came to my mind. First, as experts of artistic fields, our need for modeling the complex oversimplifies it. A wine can be both flawless and bad if your sole metrics are the acidity and sugar levels. In the same spirit, the quality standards of a building today concerns itself mostly with practicality and safety. When optimized for, these produce the perfectly optimal shape of a cat carrier.</p> <p>Second, our incentives do not reflect the remaining aspects of a beautiful design, as whatever effort not included in the optimization task is spent on reducing costs. Hence, that cat carrier is left as raw concrete, without any color or decoration.</p> <p>Third, our desire to avoid failure, both as an expert and as an artistic human being, prevents us from pushing forward. As a gray cat box in the name of a living space is obviously insulting to humanity, and yet there is no clear path in our simple model to improve upon it, we have successfully found an excuse and called it brutalist, so that it finds a valid place in our field of expertise.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/IMG_0969-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/IMG_0969-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/IMG_0969-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/IMG_0969.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">The Barbican, London. A likeable example of brutalism.</figcaption> </figure> <p>Yet, however much the current teachings empty out their meaning, what we build today is not brutalist like the Barbican, just as a scientifically perfect 1980s Pinot from Burgundy is not a good wine <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. What we have today is evasive architecture, evading costs and risks, as well as the common beauty, somewhat like software developers in a large bank evading open source in favor of an IBM mainframe.</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>An important article on the topic from Michel Bettane: <a href="https://www.mybettanedesseauve.fr/2024/07/15/la-bourgogne-limpasse-et-lissue">https://www.mybettanedesseauve.fr/2024/07/15/la-bourgogne-limpasse-et-lissue</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="architecture"/><category term="architecture,"/><category term="art,"/><category term="brutalism,"/><category term="evasive-architecture"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring evasiveness in architecture and other artistic fields.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Three pillars of love</title><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/three-pillars-of-love/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three pillars of love"/><published>2025-01-01T00:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-01T00:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/three-pillars-of-love</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/three-pillars-of-love/"><![CDATA[<p>Our emotions often surge at first sight. A dress in a window, a piece of furniture in a shop, or even a book’s binding can trigger an immediate response. Yet such feelings inevitably fade with time –there is no love at first sight that persists unchanged.</p> <p>Let’s have an example through a movie. Summarizing shortly: the endearing main character of the arthouse movie “Mrs. Harris goes to Paris” loves two dresses: her initial love is for an impeccable Dior owned by her employer, a remote object of pure admiration. This love for the unachievable then transforms into a dream of acquiring her own, launching a journey that reveals the artistry and effort behind such creation. When finally presented with a different dress, she finds the beauty she is looking for immediately. For myself, this reaction raises the question: is there a difference between the love of Mrs. Harris to the initial dress, and then the latter?</p> <p>The answer lies in their foundations: we can trace the roots of her latter connection through the film’s narrative, while the former exists as mere attraction, readily replaceable by any other object of similar beauty. The second connection persists in memory, both for us as viewers and for Mrs. Harris within her story, precisely because it is anchored in experience.</p> <p>Not just any kind of experience, of course. It begins with pure admiration –that initial, unqualified choice based on subjective beauty alone. Not for the exact object itself, mind you, but something of that theme that inspires an interest, in this case, some other dress of the same designer house. That is the initial step.</p> <p>Next comes the story: the context of the object, both its history and its role in one’s personal narrative, must be substantial enough to remain in memory, to resist being forgotten or replaced. The effort of saving to pay for the dress, as well as the journey that takes Mrs. Harris deep into Dior House where she entrenches a deep respect for the designers and tailors who make these items.</p> <p>Finally, there must be ownership—not in the merely commercial sense, but as a period of genuine connection where the object’s existence becomes intertwined with one’s own, allowing for the formation of a defining bond. This happens immediately with the provision of the dress to Mrs. Harris, thus sealing a long-term bond for an impeccable piece of art.</p> <p>Then, here is my recipe for a connection that endures: admiration as the spark, respect born of understanding, and ownership that transforms appreciation into lasting attachment.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="art"/><category term="film,"/><category term="arthouse,"/><category term="love,"/><category term="art"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An analysis of lasting connections]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On the enduring dislike of contemporary art</title><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2024/contemporary-art/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the enduring dislike of contemporary art"/><published>2024-10-20T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-20T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2024/contemporary-art</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2024/contemporary-art/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/unny066l-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/unny066l-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/unny066l-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/unny066l.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">"Guernica" from Picasso. In case contemporary artists need some inspiration.</figcaption> </figure> <p>It is hard for an average person to connect with contemporary art. I had convinced myself in a theory of an “inside joke” among artists: not that they create ridiculous imagery, but they challenge themselves and each other to explore the boundaries of certain artistic dimensions. Consequently, for those who are far removed from such boundaries, the works remain indistinct. And it follows that contemporary art should not be commonplace for common people, but should be provided, in free but separate format, for artists themselves.</p> <p>Yet this theory overlooks the challenges of humanity. Although post-impressionism and all subsequent avant-garde movements followed impressionism, which itself pushed beyond academism and others in natural succession, there was a certain theme in many powerful avant-garde art that emerged through 20th century, highly connected to the pain and savagery of their era. Their own empathy assigned a certain responsibility to artists, in depicting not a utopia, but the dismembered human beings, distorted collective psyche, and all that’s lost or destroyed. This angle is valuable enough to recognize not only for critics of contemporary art, but also the artists who, in pursuing originality, might benefit from understanding why their predecessors first shattered conventional forms.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="art"/><category term="contemporary-art"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A discussion on contemporary art's deliberate inaccessibility versus its inherent sensitivity.]]></summary></entry></feed>