<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-02T10:54:09+00:00</updated><id>https://meakbiyik.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>AI researcher, entrepreneur, wine enthusiast, occasional blogger. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The ethics of hypocrisy</title><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/ethics-of-hypocrisy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ethics of hypocrisy"/><published>2025-08-02T00:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-02T00:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/ethics-of-hypocrisy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/ethics-of-hypocrisy/"><![CDATA[<p>Suppose you commit a bad deed, whose severity depends on your upbringing, culture, environment, and personal philosophy. What then?</p> <blockquote> <p>Just because there are beggars everywhere asking for money, am I supposed to simply give them some? Of course not! They need to earn it somehow.</p> </blockquote> <p>We humans are mighty adaptive, and it takes only a few repetitions to get used to something. The same applies to our own actions: you might feel guilty the first time and less guilty the second. That fading guilt comes from our internal justification, which always seems perfectly reasonable. It has to—after all, is it acceptable to feel bad every time it happens?</p> <blockquote> <p>Killing animals is wrong, and eating them almost always requires an act of killing. But I’ve already done it many times; am I supposed to drown in guilt as well?</p> </blockquote> <p>It’s painful to live with a broken personal philosophy. Your internal arguments stop making sense; it feels like arguing with someone who has memory issues. Sometimes it’s better to hand over a few coins to the beggars, or to acknowledge the guilt and push through it for a few minutes, rather than driving your mind into an early grave.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ethics"/><category term="ethics,"/><category term="hypocrisy,"/><category term="personal"/><category term="philosophy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[And why should you feel bad about not giving money to beggars]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Patronage reimagined</title><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/mode-collapse-in-art/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patronage reimagined"/><published>2025-07-27T00:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-27T00:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/mode-collapse-in-art</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/mode-collapse-in-art/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/post-3-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/post-3-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/post-3-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/post-3-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Pixelwald Turicum. A fantastic, 15-minute experience in the Merzbacher collection of the Kunsthaus, Zurich.</figcaption> </figure> <p>Art has changed, so has its funding. Before there was patronage, and artists created the artworks for the whims of their patrons. Today, public funds flow through ministerial projects or artist collectives, creating influential movements through collaboration.</p> <p>However healthy and independent this might seem, it births a lack of governance. Museums fund artists and showcase their work, primarily benefiting that small group of high-profile artists. Walk through any European city, and you’ll find classical art museums noisy as a bazaar while contemporary ones having a hard time filling their ample, sterile space. Yes, this is also a numbers game: classical museums simply house more. But accessibility plays its part too, as thematic clarity and reduced abstraction actually attract audiences.</p> <p>The disconnect between the artistic development and public fancy arguably stems from a <strong>mode collapse</strong>: allow a sufficiently small system (in this case high-profile art) to self-improve, and you risk creating a misaligned device, outputting incomprehensible artifacts. The evolution towards pop art and meta art <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> is a result of such collapse under capitalist pressure.</p> <p>This is <strong>not</strong> an argument to stop public funding, or to supervise art. Neither should we banish contemporary art from museums. However, artists need better access to the psyche of today’s public, and public museums, if they are to host their art, should expect such understanding.</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>An important article on the topic from Michel Bettane: <a href="https://www.mybettanedesseauve.fr/2024/07/15/la-bourgogne-limpasse-et-lissue">https://www.mybettanedesseauve.fr/2024/07/15/la-bourgogne-limpasse-et-lissue</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="art"/><category term="art,"/><category term="contemporary"/><category term="art,"/><category term="mode"/><category term="collapse"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Avoiding mode collapse through balancing artistic freedom with public engagement]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Campo Hermoso —and what to do with great beans</title><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/campo-hermoso/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Campo Hermoso —and what to do with great beans"/><published>2025-07-13T06:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-13T06:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/campo-hermoso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/campo-hermoso/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/post-2-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/post-2-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/post-2-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/post-2-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Campo Hermoso.</figcaption> </figure> <p>I got acquainted with this fantastic producer from the similarly-named coffee subregion of Colombia through a filter coffee I had in Zürich. Our local roastery that packaged these beans, Jack LeFleur, had made a couple of fantastic roasts lately, but their Campo Hermoso pink bourbon is probably the highlight of their selection: intense strawberry and red berries, great body and length.</p> <p>After having it as a filter coffee, I bought a 125g bag and started experimenting with it at home. Despite my best efforts, I simply could not make an espresso with it that was drinkable by itself. My Mini Gaggia delivered stable but nevertheless either sour or bitter notes, and even the most balanced pull was quite aggressive.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/post-2-2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/post-2-2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/post-2-2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/post-2-2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">The tastiest food with the adjective "Red Velvet"</figcaption> </figure> <p>Now I have started rethinking this bean as I tasted it again, in a completely different place by a different roastery. Here in Hong Kong, the Urban Coffee Roaster is making a fantastic drink they call “Red Velvet Irish Coffee.” The “red velvet” here does not come from any artificial coloring or sweetener, but rather from the aroma profile of the Campo Hermoso Geisha beans, with a spectacular length only extended by the whiskey inside.</p> <p>The whole experience made me think: do we need high pressure at all if we can improve bean production and roasting? With enough body, intensity, and acidity that one can serve it with cream and whiskey, do you need further extraction? Going one step further, could one even serve this pour-over with milk as a latte, and if so, do we need to reconsider what we need for a complete coffee lineup in a cafe? Rather than a bulky espresso machine, perhaps a simple diner filter device pouring us cups and cups of strawberries, to be served as you wish. That’s some dream.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/post-2-3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/post-2-3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/post-2-3-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/post-2-3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">The beautiful old lady looking over her subjects. The mighty Mini Gaggia.</figcaption> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="food"/><category term="coffee"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abolishing pressure from coffee.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fine dining in Istanbul</title><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/fine-dining-in-istanbul/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fine dining in Istanbul"/><published>2025-07-06T06:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-06T06:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/fine-dining-in-istanbul</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/fine-dining-in-istanbul/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/post-1-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/post-1-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/post-1-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/post-1-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Cats.</figcaption> </figure> <p>Making the best out of a transfer flight, I recently had an insightful day in Istanbul. I saw a couple of Ottoman impressionists at the Istanbul Museum of Painting and Sculpture, visited two worthwhile restaurants, and saw a few cats, as usual. Let me write a few words about the food.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/post-1-2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/post-1-2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/post-1-2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/post-1-2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">The signature dish of Yeni Lokanta, mantı.</figcaption> </figure> <p><strong>Yeni Lokanta</strong>, my lunch spot. Tastefully decorated, eerily empty, great service. Most importantly, it has one of the most ingenious menus for refined Turkish cuisine. It feels as if the menu was based on a traditional Turkish dining experience but brought into the Western style, rather than simply introducing Turkish ideas into existing French courses. The first indicator of this is the bread and butter service; starting with an açma con mahlep and sadeyağ (ghee) is such an obvious decision for a Turkish person, yet this was my first time seeing it. Then, the mantı: they make the dish itself and improve upon the sauce in such a way that it becomes a signature of the restaurant. A great mindset! This contrasts with another dish, the çiğ köfte tartare. I also liked it, yet it was a French dish through and through, just with some isot and sumac. I prefer the former approach to course design over the latter. As a side note, the cheese/pastırma börek is not a well-designed plate; avoid it. Otherwise, it’s an absolute must-visit. Get the Vinkara Kalecik Karası Reserve 2020 as the wine.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/post-1-3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/post-1-3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/post-1-3-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/post-1-3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">The best Turkish red of the year, Barolo incarnate.</figcaption> </figure> <p><strong>Neolokal</strong>, the dinner spot. It has the same mindset as Yeni Lokanta, executed quite well—admittedly, for that price, anything less would be unacceptable. The fixed menu truly represents Turkish cuisine. What a great lahana sarma! The fish cookery was also wonderful; both the bonito and the haddock were impeccable.</p> <p>Yet, two patterns of failure that persist in Turkish fine dining continue here.</p> <p>First is the inability to cook great lamb. The mutancana was good, of course, but if you cook a piece of lamb for hours with fruit, then mash and cube it, you don’t really trust yourself to create meat with a good texture, do you? OD Urla had a very similar dish a few years ago (with coffee grounds)—similarly cubed tandır-just a sad plate. It’s not even close to Aşçı Bacaksız, nor the goat made at Yedi Mehmet. Frankly, I make better tandır at home (the trick is to use a 1:1 ratio of lamb fat to meat).</p> <p>The second failure follows a similar theme of mishandling a classic: the baklava. I don’t think there’s much to discuss about the dish itself, but here’s an important insight: Baklava, as it’s made in Antep, is possibly the most highly engineered dish in Turkish cuisine. If you can’t improve upon it, either just serve one purchased from Antep or don’t serve it at all. The second dessert, Frigo, tasted better than the baklava, which was served with a horrendous ice cream. It was both infuriating and sad.</p> <p>Now, of course, the text above is not gentle. Would I recommend Neolokal, though? Absolutely! It was the best fine dining experience I have had in Turkey so far. I need to visit TURK soon, though.</p> <p>Thanks for the meal!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="food"/><category term="food,"/><category term="wine,"/><category term="turkish"/><category term="cuisine,"/><category term="istanbul"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Making the best out of a transfer flight, I recently had an insightful day in Istanbul.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Three pillars of love</title><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/three-pillars-of-love/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three pillars of love"/><published>2025-04-24T00:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-24T00:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/three-pillars-of-love</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/three-pillars-of-love/"><![CDATA[<p>Our emotions often surge at first sight. A dress in a window, a piece of furniture in a shop, or even a book’s binding can trigger an immediate response. Yet such feelings inevitably fade with time – there is no love at first sight that persists unchanged.</p> <p>This initial feeling is essentially attraction, compelling yet often superficial. It can be readily replaceable by any other object of similar appeal because it lacks deeper roots. A connection that truly endures, however, possesses a different foundation. It persists in memory precisely because it is anchored in experience.</p> <p>What kind of experience builds this lasting connection? It begins with pure admiration — that initial, unqualified choice based on subjective beauty alone. This serves as the necessary spark, an interest inspired not necessarily by the exact object, but perhaps by something of its kind or theme. That is the initial step.</p> <p>Next comes the story: the context of the object. Both its own history and its developing role in one’s personal narrative must be substantial enough to remain in memory, to resist being forgotten or replaced. Gaining understanding of this context, perhaps through learning, effort, or personal journey related to the object, builds a deeper respect.</p> <p>Finally, there must be ownership—not in the merely commercial sense, but experienced as a period of genuine connection. This is where the object’s existence becomes truly intertwined with one’s own, allowing for the formation of a defining, personal bond.</p> <p>Then, here is a recipe for a connection that endures: admiration as the spark, respect born of understanding the object’s story and context, and ownership or genuine connection that transforms appreciation into lasting attachment.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="art"/><category term="love,"/><category term="art"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An analysis of lasting connections]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The unsightly science of architecture</title><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/evasive-architecture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The unsightly science of architecture"/><published>2025-01-01T00:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-01T00:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/evasive-architecture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2025/evasive-architecture/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/photo_2025-01-01_17-25-42-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/photo_2025-01-01_17-25-42-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/photo_2025-01-01_17-25-42-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/photo_2025-01-01_17-25-42.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Kornhaus over the Limmat river, Zürich. The grey middle finger.</figcaption> </figure> <p>I asked many architecture students in Zürich what they thought of Kornhaus, a local symbol of brutalism. Most seemed bored by the question, possibly due to the regularity of the event, and the contempt in their response correlated with their appreciation of the building. “Concrete,” one said, “the choice of concrete and other materials”, when I asked what made that grey rectangle remarkable.</p> <p>As with these students building our bleak, rectangular future, I have talked with other weary experts. One regionally renowned wine critic, when I inquired, used “flawless” as his highest praise about some soulless, oaky red wine. A gourmet described their branch of celery as “crunchy and delicious” in the second course of their fancy fine dining experience. I asked myself then: what unites these exhausted groups of people, showing the tendency to gratify a simple and ugly option over any other?</p> <p>Three reasons came to my mind. First, as experts of artistic fields, our need for modeling the complex oversimplifies it. A wine can be both flawless and bad if your sole metrics are the acidity and sugar levels. In the same spirit, the quality standards of a building today concerns itself mostly with practicality and safety. When optimized for, these produce the perfectly optimal shape of a cat carrier.</p> <p>Second, our incentives do not reflect the remaining aspects of a beautiful design, as whatever effort not included in the optimization task is spent on reducing costs. Hence, that cat carrier is left as raw concrete, without any color or decoration.</p> <p>Third, our desire to avoid failure, both as an expert and as an artistic human being, prevents us from pushing forward. As a gray cat box in the name of a living space is obviously insulting to humanity, and yet there is no clear path in our simple model to improve upon it, we have successfully found an excuse and called it brutalist, so that it finds a valid place in our field of expertise.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/IMG_0969-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/IMG_0969-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/IMG_0969-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/IMG_0969.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">The Barbican, London. A likeable example of brutalism.</figcaption> </figure> <p>Yet, however much the current teachings empty out their meaning, what we build today is not brutalist like the Barbican, just as a scientifically perfect 1980s Pinot from Burgundy is not a good wine <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. What we have today is evasive architecture, evading costs and risks, as well as the common beauty, somewhat like software developers in a large bank evading open source in favor of an IBM mainframe.</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>An important article on the topic from Michel Bettane: <a href="https://www.mybettanedesseauve.fr/2024/07/15/la-bourgogne-limpasse-et-lissue">https://www.mybettanedesseauve.fr/2024/07/15/la-bourgogne-limpasse-et-lissue</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="architecture"/><category term="architecture,"/><category term="art,"/><category term="brutalism,"/><category term="evasive-architecture"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Evasiveness in architecture and other artistic fields.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The enduring dislike of contemporary art</title><link href="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2024/contemporary-art/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The enduring dislike of contemporary art"/><published>2024-10-20T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-20T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2024/contemporary-art</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://meakbiyik.com/blog/2024/contemporary-art/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/unny066l-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/unny066l-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/unny066l-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/unny066l.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">"Guernica" from Picasso. In case contemporary artists need some inspiration.</figcaption> </figure> <p>It is hard for an average person to connect with contemporary art. I had convinced myself in a theory of an “inside joke” among artists: not that they create ridiculous imagery, but they challenge themselves and each other to explore the boundaries of certain artistic dimensions. Consequently, for those who are far removed from such boundaries, the works remain indistinct. And it follows that contemporary art should not be commonplace for common people, but should be provided, in free but separate format, for artists themselves.</p> <p>Yet this theory overlooks the challenges of humanity. Although post-impressionism and all subsequent avant-garde movements followed impressionism, which itself pushed beyond academism and others in natural succession, there was a certain theme in many powerful avant-garde art that emerged through 20th century, highly connected to the pain and savagery of their era. Their own empathy assigned a certain responsibility to artists, in depicting not a utopia, but the dismembered human beings, distorted collective psyche, and all that’s lost or destroyed. This angle is valuable enough to recognize not only for critics of contemporary art, but also the artists who, in pursuing originality, might benefit from understanding why their predecessors first shattered conventional forms.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="art"/><category term="contemporary-art"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Contemporary art's deliberate inaccessibility versus its inherent sensitivity.]]></summary></entry></feed>